<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/home/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/home/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-08-05T23:51:34-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/home/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Marc Morcos - Portfolio</title><subtitle>Portfolio displaying some of my projects.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">About Me</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/home/my-interests/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About Me" /><published>2024-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/home/my-interests</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/home/my-interests/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/final-edited.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I’m a computer engineering graduate with a keen interest in software development and robotics.</p>

<p>I taught myself C++ through YouTube tutorials at a young age, sparking a passion for programming. Over the years, this passion has grown, as I’ve worked on various personal projects, including 3D printers, Raspberry Pi-based robotics, an infrared camera rock-paper-scissors program, and DIY VR headsets.</p>

<p>During my Computer Engineering degree at the University of Toronto, I was immersed in coursework covering software, hardware, and mechanical engineering. Achieving the highest fourth-year grade in the Computer engineering department for my year, and obtaining a minor in robotics and a certificate in AI, reflects my commitment to academic excellence.</p>

<p>As a former intern at Epson, I played active roles in robotics, AI, and software development. I took ownership of three tools, extended other ROS-based tools, converted experimental technologies into practical solutions, and presented innovative ideas to the department.</p>

<p>I’m eager to expand my knowledge and skills further, always excited about learning new technologies and meeting new people.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">W.S. Wilson Medal</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/home/w-s-wilson-award/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="W.S. Wilson Medal" /><published>2024-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/home/w-s-wilson-award</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/home/w-s-wilson-award/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/cropped.jpg?w=1004" alt="" /></p>

<p>I am happy to announce that I am the recipient of the University of Toronto’s W.S. Wilson Medal, awarded to the student with the highest final year average in computer engineering. Reflecting on my journey at UofT, I am incredibly grateful for the friends, mentors and experiences that have shaped me. Without them, this accomplishment would not have been possible. <a href="https://undergrad.engineering.utoronto.ca/news/award-winners-2023-2024/">More Info.</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Realtime AI Verbal Conversation Assistant - Capstone</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/home/realtime-ai-verbal-conversation-assistant-capstone/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Realtime AI Verbal Conversation Assistant - Capstone" /><published>2024-05-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-05-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/home/realtime-ai-verbal-conversation-assistant-capstone</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/home/realtime-ai-verbal-conversation-assistant-capstone/"><![CDATA[<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/logonobackground.png?w=376)

<figcaption>

Logo for Conversational Assistant App

</figcaption>

</figure>

<h3 id="overview">Overview</h3>

<p>As part of my capstone project, I contributed to the development of ConvoAssistant, an Android application designed to improve reflective listening skills. Reflective listening is a crucial communication technique where the listener paraphrases their conversation partner’s message to foster deeper understanding and connection (similarly to the <a href="https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/2021/11/07/ai-chatbot-summer-research/">smoking cessation AI chatbot</a>). Our project leverages advanced AI technology to assist users in mastering this skill, enhancing their overall communication effectiveness.</p>

<h3 id="certificate-of-distinction">Certificate of Distinction</h3>

<p>I’m proud to share that our team, Capstone Team 2023692, was awarded a Certificate of Distinction for our outstanding work on the ConvoAssistant project. This recognition was a testament to our innovative approach, technical proficiency, and dedication to enhancing reflective listening skills through advanced AI technology. Receiving this certificate not only validated our hard work and collaboration but also underscored the impact of our project in the field of communication enhancement.</p>

<h3 id="project-objectives">Project Objectives</h3>

<p>The primary objective of the project was to create an application that aids users in developing reflective listening skills through two distinct modes:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Real-Time Assistant (RTA) Mode:</strong> This mode assists users during live conversations by providing reflective statements based on the ongoing dialogue. It is designed for deep, thoughtful conversations where users have time to consider their responses. Specifically, it listens to a verbal conversation and suggests responses through the user’s earbuds.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Practice Mode:</strong> This mode generates scenarios for users to practice reflective listening. After reflecting on these scenarios, the application evaluates the user’s responses and offers constructive feedback for improvement.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="implementation">Implementation</h3>

<p>The application serves as a verbal interface for a Large Language Model (LLM), specifically OpenAI’s GPT-3.5 turbo model. Here’s a breakdown of the technical implementation:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Audio Input and Output:</strong> The application takes audio input from the user, converts it to text, and processes it using the LLM. The generated text response is then converted back to audio to be played aloud to the user.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Speaker Diarization:</strong> In RTA Mode, Google Cloud’s Speech diarization platform is utilized to identify distinct speakers within a conversation, ensuring accurate reflective statements.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Feedback Mechanism:</strong> In Practice Mode, the application not only evaluates the user’s reflective responses but also provides suggestions for improvement, fostering a continuous learning environment.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Android Application</strong>: The application was developed using Kotlin within an Android Studio Project.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/image.png?w=300)

<figcaption>

Android Application Interface

</figcaption>

</figure>

<h3 id="development-and-evaluation">Development and Evaluation</h3>

<p>The project development followed a structured approach, with regular updates and milestones tracked through Gantt charts. We adhered to strict requirements and specifications to ensure the application’s functionality, responsiveness, and efficiency. The final product was thoroughly tested and passed evaluations with high marks for both response time and accuracy.</p>

<h3 id="key-contributions">Key Contributions</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Design and Implementation:</strong> Participated in designing the android application’s architecture and implementing key features such as audio processing and integration with GPT-3.5 turbo.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Testing and Evaluation:</strong> Conducted extensive testing to ensure the application met performance benchmarks and provided accurate, timely responses.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>User Experience:</strong> Focused on creating an intuitive user interface that facilitates seamless interaction, making it easy for users to engage with the application in both modes.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="outcome">Outcome</h3>

<p>ConvoAssistant successfully accomplishes its goal of facilitating reflective listening in users, providing a practical tool for improving communication skills. The project showcases my ability to apply advanced AI technology to solve real-world problems and enhance user experiences.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>This project exemplifies the intersection of technology and communication, demonstrating how AI can be harnessed to improve essential interpersonal skills.</p>

<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/poster.png?w=1024)

<figcaption>

Final Project Poster

</figcaption>

</figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Robot Modeling Course - ECE470</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/home/robot-modeling-course-ece470/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Robot Modeling Course - ECE470" /><published>2024-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/home/robot-modeling-course-ece470</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/home/robot-modeling-course-ece470/"><![CDATA[<p>In the ECE470 course, I was immersed in an exploration of robot modeling, forward and inverse kinematics for robot arms. This course delves into the intricate mechanics of robotic systems, offering valuable insights into their design and movement.</p>

<p><img src="https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/small2-2.gif?w=180" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Key Learnings:</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Robot Modeling:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Acquiring a deep understanding of the principles and methodologies involved in modeling robot arms.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Exploring various modeling techniques to represent the dynamics and geometry of robotic systems.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Forward and Inverse Kinematics:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Delving into forward kinematics to predict the end-effector’s position based on joint variables.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Unraveling the complexities of inverse kinematics to determine the required joint configurations for a desired end-effector position.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Path Planning Challenges:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Tackling the complexities of path planning in the context of robot arms.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Engaging with the nuances of gradient descent to navigate a path laden with obstacles, fostering problem-solving skills in real-world scenarios.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>In the course’s labs, I got to create path planning code for the robot to draw images. For example, I got the robot to draw a self-portrait on paper.</p>

<p><img src="https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/creativepatternkukabot.jpg?w=771" alt="" /></p>

<p>In another lab, I used the artificial potential method to do path planning, picking up an object and avoiding obstacles to place it at a goal position.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the ECE470 course, I was immersed in an exploration of robot modeling, forward and inverse kinematics for robot arms. This course delves into the intricate mechanics of robotic systems, offering valuable insights into their design and movement.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Distraction Free Social Media Browser</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/home/distraction-free-social-media-browser/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Distraction Free Social Media Browser" /><published>2024-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/home/distraction-free-social-media-browser</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/home/distraction-free-social-media-browser/"><![CDATA[<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/android-studio-icon-486x512-zp9um7zl.png?w=486)

<figcaption>

Android Studio Logo [Image from Source \[3\]](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/references/)

</figcaption>

</figure>

<p>In a conscious effort to reclaim valuable time from social media, I recognized the need to maintain a connection with friends while minimizing distractions. This realization inspired me to embark on the creation of my own distraction-free social media browsing app. Leveraging Android Studio and the Kotlin programming language, which I was concurrently learning for other projects, I set out to enhance my skills and craft a tool that aligned with my personal goals.</p>

<p><strong>Key Project Highlights:</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Purposeful Design:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Developed the app with a specific focus on minimizing distractions, allowing for efficient and intentional communication with friends.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Tailored the user experience to prioritize messaging functionalities over extraneous features.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Skill Enhancement Through Development:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Utilized Android Studio and Kotlin for app development, furthering my proficiency in these technologies.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Embraced a continuous improvement mindset, consistently refining and optimizing the app to align with evolving needs and insights.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Personal Development Journey:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Time Management and Prioritization:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>The project was born out of a deliberate decision to allocate time away from social media to more impactful endeavors.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>By crafting a purposeful social media browsing app, I demonstrated a commitment to intentional time management and project prioritization.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Continuous Learning and Improvement:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Actively engaged in the learning process by using Android Studio and Kotlin, simultaneously applying acquired knowledge to the development of a real-world application.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Embraced the ethos of continuous improvement by regularly updating and refining the app on GitHub, showcasing dedication to skill enhancement.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>GitHub Repository:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>The project is publicly accessible on GitHub at <a href="https://github.com/MarcM0/Instagram-Messenger">Instagram-Messenger</a>, providing transparency and an opportunity for collaboration and feedback from the developer community.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Career Relevance:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Application Development Skills:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>The project significantly contributed to honing my application development skills, with a particular focus on mobile platforms.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>The experience gained is directly transferable to potential roles in mobile app development and showcases my ability to conceive, design, and implement purpose-driven applications.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Self-Directed Learning:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>The decision to create a distraction-free social media app underscores my initiative in self-directed learning and the practical application of acquired knowledge.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Such self-motivated projects are indicative of a proactive approach that aligns with the dynamic nature of the tech industry.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Conclusion:</strong></p>

<p>The development of the distraction-free social media browsing app is a testament to my commitment to intentional living and continuous self-improvement. Through this project, I not only strengthened my skills in Android Studio and Kotlin but also demonstrated a keen awareness of the value of time and focus in personal and professional pursuits. As I progress in my career, the lessons learned from this project will undoubtedly influence my approach to technology, emphasizing purposeful and impactful innovation.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SmallC Compiler - ECE467</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/home/smallc-compiler/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SmallC Compiler - ECE467" /><published>2024-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/home/smallc-compiler</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/home/smallc-compiler/"><![CDATA[<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/compiler.png?w=1000)

<figcaption>

[  
Photo from Source \[2\]](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/references/) Compiler diagram

</figcaption>

</figure>

<p>In my ECE467 (compilers) class, I undertook the development of a compiler for a subset of C, termed SmallC. This comprehensive project not only tested my programming skills but also deepened my understanding of compiler construction and optimization techniques.</p>

<p><strong>Key Contributions:</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Grammar Definition and Parser Implementation:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Created a formal grammar for SmallC and implemented a robust parser using ANTLR4.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Translated parsed code into an abstract syntax tree (AST), laying the foundation for subsequent processing steps.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Semantic Checker in C++:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Developed a semantic checker in C++ to ensure code adherence to SmallC language standards.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>This step was crucial in identifying and rectifying potential errors before code generation.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Intermediate Code Generation:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Generated intermediate code from the validated AST, a pivotal step in making the code platform-independent.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Set the stage for further optimization and eventual translation to machine-specific code.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Insights into Optimization Techniques:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Learned about optimization passes, gaining insights into how compilers enhance code efficiency.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Key Takeaways:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Holistic Understanding of Compilation Process:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Gained a comprehensive understanding of the compilation process from parsing and semantic checking to code generation and optimization.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Developed skills to address challenges at each stage of the compiler pipeline.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Impact on Coding Practices:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Acquired valuable insights into how code is compiled and optimized, directly influencing my day-to-day coding practices.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Strengthened ability to write efficient and optimized code by leveraging compiler principles.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Conclusion:</strong></p>

<p>The SmallC Compiler project in ECE467 was a pivotal experience that sharpened my programming and problem-solving skills while providing a holistic understanding of the intricate compilation process. This endeavor not only expanded my knowledge in compiler construction but also equipped me with practical insights applicable to future coding endeavors.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Inverted Pendulum Stabilization - ECE410</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/home/inverted-pendulum-stabilization-ece410/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inverted Pendulum Stabilization - ECE410" /><published>2024-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/home/inverted-pendulum-stabilization-ece410</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/home/inverted-pendulum-stabilization-ece410/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/small3-1.gif?w=288" alt="" /></p>

<p>The highlight of my ECE 410 course was the hands-on implementation of advanced control theory through the Inverted Pendulum project. This ambitious endeavor not only reinforced my theoretical understanding of robotics control but also showcased my ability to apply this knowledge to real-world challenges.</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Theoretical Mastery:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Acquired in-depth knowledge in advanced control concepts, including Kalman decomposition, state feedback stabilization, optimal control, and integral control.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Applied these theoretical foundations specifically to the challenging dynamics of stabilizing an inverted pendulum on a moving cart.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Practical Application:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Utilized MATLAB and Simulink to model and simulate various control algorithms for the inverted pendulum system.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Translated theoretical models into practical solutions, emphasizing the complexities of real-world dynamics.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Hardware-Software Integration:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Implemented controllers on an Arduino board.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Overcame the challenges of real-time control, validating the effectiveness of theoretical control strategies in a physical environment.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Significance of the Inverted Pendulum Project:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Demonstrated Application of Theory:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>The project served as a tangible demonstration of how advanced control theories can be applied to solve complex real-world problems.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Successfully stabilizing the inverted pendulum highlighted the practical implications of theoretical concepts in robotics control.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Gained first hand experience in the difference between simulated performance, and real performance with disturbances.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Skill Development:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Developed a unique skill set in designing, simulating, and implementing control strategies specifically tailored for challenging systems like the inverted pendulum.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Gained proficiency in troubleshooting and fine-tuning controllers for dynamic physical systems.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The Inverted Pendulum project in ECE 410 stands out as a pivotal experience, underscoring the practical application of advanced control theories. This project not only solidified my understanding of robotics control but also demonstrated my capacity to tackle complex challenges at the intersection of theory and application. As I move forward, the lessons learned from this project will undoubtedly shape my contributions to the field of robotics and automation.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mechanical Engineering Design (MIE243)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/home/mechanical-engineering-design-mie243/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mechanical Engineering Design (MIE243)" /><published>2021-11-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-11-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/home/mechanical-engineering-design-mie243</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/home/mechanical-engineering-design-mie243/"><![CDATA[<p>I took a mechanical engineering design course to feed my curiosity, and expand my breadth of knowledge in the field of robotics. Whether I have to design some simple mechanical parts, or work with mechanical engineers in a robotics context, I will be well equipped.</p>

<p>I found the course extremely interesting. Through hands on projects, I learned how to design machines from a mechanical design perspective, and how to bring those ideas to life in CAD (Computer Aided Design) software like SolidWorks. In fact, I was able to pass the CSWA (Certified SOLIDWORKS Associate) test with flying colors, becoming SolidWorks certified.</p>

<h2 id="dissections">Dissections</h2>

<p>During the semester, we had group dissections, where we dissected existing mechanisms to better understand them. We cadded the mechanisms using SolidWorks, modified them, and analyzed their strengths and weaknesses. We also learned to make engineering drawings both by hand, and using solidworks.</p>

<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/1-1.gif?w=310)

<figcaption>

One of the assemblies I made in SolidWorks for an electric screwdriver

</figcaption>

</figure>

<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/image-12.png?w=1024)

<figcaption>

An engineering drawing I made in SolidWorks

</figcaption>

</figure>

<p>Later in the course, we designed our own gearbox and had it 3D printed. I was well prepared for this due to my <a href="https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/2021/11/07/3d-printing/">previous experience with 3D printing</a>. We had to print our parts within a strict printing time limit. This limited the amount of material we could print. However, we were able to use this limited material to still make a relatively durable design.</p>

<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/image-10.png?w=465)

<figcaption>

Casing Design

</figcaption>

</figure>

<p>The final result was a simple elegant design that met all the design specification, ready weeks in advance of the deadline.</p>

<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/image-11.png?w=1024)

<figcaption>

3D Printed Final Dissection Design

</figcaption>

</figure>

<h2 id="designing-a-cnc-mill">Designing a CNC Mill</h2>

<p>The overarching project in this course was to design our own CNC milling machine. My team used everything we had learned in this course, from specific mechanisms to the engineering design process as a whole. Before we had learned to use SolidWorks, I used tinkerCAD to make some simple candidate designs.</p>

<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/image-13.png?w=482)

<figcaption>

My candidate design made in tinkerCAD

</figcaption>

</figure>

<p>After many iterations of candidate designs, as well as mechanism selection, my team was able to start creating our final design. We modelled this final design in SolidWorks, using both our own original parts, and parts supplied by manufacturer websites. I worked on multiple subsystems, including the movement axes, the frame, and the automatic tool changer.</p>

<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/image.png?w=880)

<figcaption>

Final Assembly (with protective acrylic cover removed)

</figcaption>

</figure>

<p>The final result was a full CAD for the CNC machine, which was thoroughly analyzed to ensure that all requirements were met and/or exceeded.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I took a mechanical engineering design course to feed my curiosity, and expand my breadth of knowledge in the field of robotics. Whether I have to design some simple mechanical parts, or work with mechanical engineers in a robotics context, I will be well equipped.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">3D Printing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/home/3d-printing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="3D Printing" /><published>2021-11-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-11-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/home/3d-printing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/home/3d-printing/"><![CDATA[<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/1.png?w=592)

<figcaption>

Building the original 3D printer

</figcaption>

</figure>

<p>Between grade 9 and 10, my fascination with 3D printing led me to embark on a challenging yet rewarding endeavor – building my original 3D printer from a Kickstarter kit. Despite being a novice at the time and facing numerous mechanical and electrical challenges within the kit, I persevered. Through meticulous troubleshooting and a deep dive into 3D printing best practices, I successfully addressed the issues and achieved the capability to print basic shapes.</p>

<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/1.jpg?w=1024)

<figcaption>

Building the original 3D printer

</figcaption>

</figure>

<p><strong>Key Milestones:</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Overcoming Challenges:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Tackled mechanical oversights and electrical failures within the kit, demonstrating resilience and problem-solving skills.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Invested significant time in addressing the printer’s issues, laying the foundation for hands-on learning.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Return to 3D Printing:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Years later, leveraged my experiences to invest in an established, pre-assembled 3D printer while staying within budget.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Applied lessons learned from the original printer to achieve consistent print quality and establish a small 3D printing service.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/3.jpg?w=677)

<figcaption>

New printer in action

</figcaption>

</figure>

<p><strong>Skills Acquired:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Technical Knowledge:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Developed expertise in endstops, motor drivers, and stepper motors during the construction of the original 3D printer.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Acquired a comprehensive understanding of 3D printing best practices, applicable in various engineering domains.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Business and Time Management:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Established and operated a small 3D printing service, gaining insights into CAD software and running a business.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Honed essential skills in expense and time management, crucial elements in any engineering career.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Implications for Robotics Career:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Applicability to Robotics:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>The knowledge gained in working with endstops, motor drivers, and stepper motors extends beyond 3D printing, finding relevance in various robotics applications.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Experience in 3D printing contributes to rapid prototyping skills, a valuable asset in the iterative development process of robotics projects.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Time and Budget Management:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>The acquired skills in managing time and budget during the 3D printing service directly align with the demands of engineering projects in any field, emphasizing their importance.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Conclusion:</strong></p>

<p>Building and operating 3D printers, from the challenging inception of the original kit to the establishment of a 3D printing service, has been a transformative journey. This experience not only deepened my technical knowledge but also honed my problem-solving and business skills. As I venture into a career in robotics, the lessons learned from this project will undoubtedly serve as a solid foundation for success.</p>

<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/4.jpg?w=1024)

<figcaption>

Some prints from the new printer

</figcaption>

</figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">“Useless” Box - Grade 11 Coding</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/home/useless-box/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Useless” Box - Grade 11 Coding" /><published>2021-11-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-11-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/home/useless-box</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/home/useless-box/"><![CDATA[<p>During my grade 11 coding course, we were given the freedom to choose a project, and my team enthusiastically decided to create a “useless” box, a whimsical device that deactivates itself when clicked. Leveraging a Raspberry Pi board and a relay, we embarked on a journey that not only resulted in a fun and quirky creation but also provided invaluable insights into coding, hardware integration, and prototyping.</p>

<figure>

![](https://marcmorcos.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-1.gif?w=414)

<figcaption>

Image of the "Useless" box

</figcaption>

</figure>

<p><strong>Key Contributions:</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Hardware Connections:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Took charge of making all the necessary connections, ensuring seamless integration of the Raspberry Pi board and the relay.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Acquired hands-on experience in hardware assembly and learned the essentials of interfacing different components.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Python Code Development:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Wrote Python code for the Raspberry Pi, orchestrating the relay to activate and deactivate at specific times.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Gained proficiency in coding for hardware control, understanding the basics of motor control through the relay.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Key Learnings:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Motor Control Basics:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Mastered the fundamentals of controlling a motor using a relay, laying a foundation for more advanced robotics projects.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Acquired practical knowledge of GPIO (General Purpose Input/Output) programming for hardware interaction.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Prototyping Skills:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Delved into the world of prototyping, understanding the importance of iterative development and troubleshooting.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Developed problem-solving skills by overcoming challenges in the hardware and software integration process.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Future Implications:</strong></p>

<p>The “useless” box project was not just a playful exploration but a valuable stepping stone for my future in robotics. The skills acquired in hardware connections, coding, and prototyping have set the stage for more complex and impactful endeavors in the field.</p>

<p><strong>Conclusion:</strong></p>

<p>Creating the Raspberry Pi-controlled “useless” box in my grade 11 coding course was a delightful and educational experience. Beyond the amusement of the project, I gained practical insights into hardware integration, coding for motor control, and the iterative process of prototyping. These skills are not only applicable in robotics but also lay the groundwork for a future filled with innovative and meaningful contributions to the field.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[During my grade 11 coding course, we were given the freedom to choose a project, and my team enthusiastically decided to create a “useless” box, a whimsical device that deactivates itself when clicked. Leveraging a Raspberry Pi board and a relay, we embarked on a journey that not only resulted in a fun and quirky creation but also provided invaluable insights into coding, hardware integration, and prototyping.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/home/assets/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>